Finding Aid for the Nancy Malone Papers PASC.0254
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nancy Malone papers
circa 1946-2000
UCLA Library Special Collections
Malone, Nancy
PASC.0254
35.0 Linear Feet (62 boxes, 2 record cartons, and 4 flat boxes)
1 Audiovisual Carriers (1 record)
4 Born-digital Carriers (4 optical discs)
Nancy Malone began her career at the age of six, modeling and appearing on live radio and television programs. She went on to become an accomplished actor, director and producer and was a co-founder of Women in Film, the nonprofit organization dedicated to supporting women's roles within the entertainment industry. The collection consists of material representing Malones' involvement in various projects as actress, director and producer, her association with Women in Film, her contributions to the advancement of the entertainment community and her various achievements outside of the industry.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Portions of collection unprocessed. Audiovisual materials are unavailable for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (spec-coll@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Malone, 2001.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9946697783606533
Biography
Nancy Malone was born in Queens Village, New York on March 19, 1935. At the age of six she started modeling and was featured on many leading, popular magazine covers. She began appearing on live radio and television programs, and was cast as Margy Martin on CBS-TV's first soap opera, The First Hundred Years. She also appeared on popular programs such as The Alcoa Hour and Hallmark Hall of Fame. She made her Broadway debut in 1952 in the title role of Ronald Alexander's comedy Time Out for Ginger, in which she was nominated for the Sarah Siddons Award in 1954. Malone got her big break in 1960 when she landed the role of Libby, the girlfriend of Detective Adam Flint on the police drama Naked City. Malone earned an Emmy nomination for outstanding performance by a supporting actress and stayed with the program until it went off the air in 1963.
During this time, Malone continued making guest appearances on other television programs such as Route 66, Dr. Kildare, and 77 Sunset Strip. From 1961 to 1963, she had a recurring role on the CBS daytime soap The Guiding Light. From 1965 to 1966, she starred on the short-lived ABC nighttime soap The Long Hot Summer, winning a Cinema Editors Award for her portrayal of Clara Varner. Following that show's cancellation, she made dozens of guest appearances on popular TV series including The Andy Griffith Show, Hawaii Five-O, The Partridge Family, Lou Grant, and Family. She also appeared as Aunt Sissy in the 1974 TV adaptation of A Tree Grows in Brooklyn, and in such theatrical films as The Man Who Loved Cat Dancing (1973) and The Trial of the Catonsville Nine (1972).
In 1971, Malone joined Tomorrow Entertainment as a story editor and was later promoted to director of motion pictures. In 1973, Malone and Tichi Wilkerson-Kassel co-founded the organization Women in Film, a support network for women in the industry. In 1975, Malone formed Lilac Productions and immediately began producing films for television. Her producing credits include the television movies Like Mom, Like Me (1978), Winner Take All (1975), and Sherlock Holmes in New York (1976), plus the television series The Bionic Woman (1976). Malone shared an Emmy for outstanding variety, music, or comedy special for her role as supervising producer on the 1993 special Bob Hope: The First 90 Years. In 1977, Malone became the first female vice president of television at 20th Century Fox, and also won the first Women in Film Crystal Award.
Malone also took up directing after completing the American Film Institute's directing workshop for women. She has directed dozens of episodes of popular television programing, including Dynasty, Diagnosis Murder, Melrose Place, Star Trek: Voyager, and Touched by an Angel. As a director she has been nominated for two Emmy Awards for episodes of Sisters (1993) and The Trials of Rosie O'Neill (1992). Her dramatic short film, Merlene of the Movies (1981) won various honors, including a Houston Film Festival award. Her television movie There Were Times, Dear (1985), was a pioneering film about Alzheimer's disease and raised over $3 million for charities. The film also won the John Muir Medical Film Festival Trustees
Malone has served on the Women in Film board of directors and as a liaison to the advisory council for the board of trustees. She has served on the faculty of the American Film Institute, helping students develop their creative talent. Additionally, she has been an instructor at UCLA, San Jose State University, the Irwin Piscator Institute of New York, and the Stella Adler Conservatory.
Biographical information from The Alliance of Women Directors, 2011 found at: http://allianceofwomendirectors.org/members/Nancy_Malone.html.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials related to the career of actress, director, producer, and activist Nancy Malone. Included are production material, scripts, business correspondence, press clippings, and a small amount of photographs associated with various projects as director and producer, some of which involved Lilac Productions, Malone's production company. Directing and producing material represents television projects such as Bob Hope: The First 90 Years, Dynasty, Hotel, Merlene of the Movies (1981), There Were Times, Dear (1985), and The Trials of Rose O' Neill. Additionally, there are photographs, clippings, and ephemera documenting stage, television, and film productions in which Malone appeared, such as Time Out for Ginger, Naked City, and Long Hot Summer, among others. Also included are files documenting Malone's involvement with Women in Film, the nonprofit organization dedicated to women's roles within the entertainment industry. There is also a small amount of material documenting Malone's contributions to the advancement of the entertainment community and her achievements outside of the industry.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Acting
Directing
Producing
Executive
Women in Film
General Career
Activism
Teaching
Art and Poetry
Philanthropic Activities
Actresses -- United States -- Archives.; Women television producers and directors -- United States -- Archives.; Malone, Nancy -- Archives; Women in Film (Organization)
- Acting
  - unspecified
    - Trial of the Cantonsville Nine (The), 1971 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      General note
      Photographs and clippings.
    - Crystal and Fox, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Photographs, clippings and a playbill.
    - Makropoulos Secret (The), 1957 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Photographs, clippings and theatre program.
    - Seven Year Itch (The), 1956 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Contract, photographs, theatre program.
    - Chalk Garden (The), 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Photographs, clippings, and theatre programs.
    - Place for Polly (A), 1969 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Photographs, theater programs, and clippings.
    - Requiem for a Heavyweight, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Clippings and San Diego theatre program.
    - Twelfth Night, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Contract, photographs, clippings, and theatre program.
    - Touch of the Poet - photographs and theatre programs, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Touch of the Poet - well wishes, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      Most of the material appears to have been removed from a scrapbook. Telegrams are fragile.
    - Touch of the Poet - clippings, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Major Barbara, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Major Barbara, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      Well wishes. Telegrams are fragile.
    - Time Out for Ginger - well wishes, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      Appears to be for opening night. Fragile telegrams.
    - Time Out for Ginger - photographs, no date (ca. 1950s) (Box 9, Folder 15)
      With photographs related to the production, television and radio appearances, Yale appearance, Girl Scouts, Malone's 18th birthday.
    - Time Out for Ginger - script, no date (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Time Out for Ginger - contracts, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Time Out for Ginger - letter from Win Stracke, 1952, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 18)
      Obituaries related to Phil Loeb and Susan Peters.
    - Time Out for Ginger - theatre programs and advertisements, 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Time Out for Ginger - clippings, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Time Out for Ginger - hotel matchbook covers from tour, no date (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Time Out for Ginger - photographs, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Opening for the Time and Life rooms at the Hotel Sherman.
    - Time Out for Ginger - drawings of Malone, no date (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Time Out for Ginger - magazine product ads, no date (Box 10, Folder 5)
      Featuring Malone.
    - Time Out for Ginger - reviews, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Time Out for Ginger - theatre programs, 1950s (Box 10, Folder 7)
      No dates.
    - Time Out for Ginger - theatre programs, 1952-1953 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Time Out for Ginger - theatre programs, 1954-1955 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Time Out for Ginger - souvenir programs, no date (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Time Out for Ginger - Theatre Arts Magazine, 1954 Feb (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Time Out for Ginger - notices for closing at Curran and Lyceum, 1953,1955 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Time Out for Ginger - letter regarding Sarah Siddons Society honor, 1954 May 26 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Naked City - clippings, 1960s, 1985, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Naked City - photographs (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Naked City - notes, no date and 1963 (Box 10, Folder 16)
      Good luck telegram from Mother and Dad and thank you letter from Dan Melnick.
    - Naked City - Emmy Awards nomination, 1963 May 26 (Box 10, Folder 18)
      Telegram regarding nomination and 15th Annual Emmy Awards program.
    - Naked City - episode titles and synopses, no date (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Material labeled "storylines".
    - Naked City - two issues of T.V. Guide and tear out, 1961 June 3, 1963 June 8 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Naked City - Museum of Broadcasting's Columbia Pictures Television: The Studio and the Creative Process exhibition, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Exhibition schedule and catalog, letters, notes, and newsletter.
    - Long Hot Summer - on the set photographs, no date (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Malone and/or Gary Conway, John Kerr, Ricardo Maltaban, Edmond O'Brien, Ruth Roman, Barry Sullivan, Roy Thinnes, Ken Peach, and other crew.
    - Long Hot Summer - clippings, 1964, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Some clippings appear to have been removed from a scrapbook.
    - Long Hot Summer - T.V. Guide issue, 1965 Sept 11 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Long Hot Summer - Frank Glicksman personal notes and photographs, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Long Hot Summer - invitations and thank you notes, 1964,1965 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Appears to be mostly work related.
    - Long Hot Summer - pilot script, 1964 Oct 7 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Nurses (The), 1977 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Appears to have also been known as T.L.C. Pitch-like presentation material, script, shooting schedule and other production information.
    - Television performances, 1946-1956 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      May include clippings, photographs, personal notes, and/or title pages from scripts related to television projects: Armstrong Circle Theatre, Arthur Murray Party, Circle of StarsDays of Grace, Forgotten Children, Kraft Television Theatre, Mama, Look Up and Live, Robert Montgomery Presents, and There's No Need to Shout.
    - Television performances, 1956-1957 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      May include clippings, photographs, personal notes, and/or title pages from scripts related to television projects: Alcoa Hour, Brillo's Star Tonight, Kraft Television Theatre, NBC Matinee Theatre, and US Steel Hour.
    - Television performances, 1957-1958 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      May include clippings, photographs, personal notes, and/or title pages from scripts related to television projects: Beesemeyer's Bungalows, The Brighter Day, Dark of Moon, Kraft Television Theatre, Look Up and Live, Modern Romances, Robert Montgomery Presents, and Trial.
    - Television performances, 1959-1963 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      May include clippings, photographs, personal notes, and/or title pages from scripts related to television projects: 77 Sunset Strip, A Clearing in the Woods, Dr. Kildare, The Fugitive, The Great Adventure, Guiding Light, Look Up and Live, Naked City, and Twilight Zone.
    - Television performances, 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      May include clippings, photographs, personal notes, and/or title pages from scripts related to television projects: Kraft Suspense Theatre, The Long Hot Summer, The Outer Limits and Route 66.
    - Television performances, 1966-1967 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      May include clippings, photographs, personal notes, and/or title pages from scripts related to television projects: Bonanza, Confidential for Women, The Fugitive, Hondo, The Outsider, Run For Your Life, and Tarzan.
    - Television performances, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      May include clippings, photographs, personal notes, and/or title pages from scripts related to television projects: The Andy Griffith Show, The Big Valley, The Flying Nun, Hawaii Five-O, Insight, Ironside, Marcus Welby, M.D., The Outcasts, The Profane Comedy, SFX, To Rome With Love.
    - Television performances, 1970-1973 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      May include clippings, photographs, personal notes, and/or title pages from scripts related to television projects: Dan August, The Girls of Huntington House, Human Dimension, Ironside, Man in the Middle, McCloud, Owen Marshall Counselor at Law, The Partridge Family and Skyway to Death.
    - Television performances, 1974-1981 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Script title pages for Cannon, Cruisin', Family, Gemini Man, Heaven Help Us, James at 15, Lucas Tanner, McMillan and Wife, and The Rockford Files.
    - Tree Grows in Brooklyn (A) - script, 1973 Dec 5 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Fright, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      Photographs, clippings and title page from script. Also known as Spell of the Hypnotist or I Cast No Shadow.
    - Violators (The), no date (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Photographs, clippings and title page from script.
    - Affair of the Skin (An), 1963 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Clippings and title page from script.
    - Intimacy, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Trial of the Cantonsville Nine (The), 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Man Who Loved Cat Dancing (The), 1973 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Capricorn One, 1973 Apr 2 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      Photograph and title page from script.
    - Time Out for Ginger - clippings, 1952 Dec 22, no date (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - USO Appearance, 1954 Aug-Sept (Box 40, Folder 5)
      Newsletters and photograph.
    - LIFE magazine cover featuring Nancy Malone, 1946 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - Dating Game (The) - contract and photographs, 1966 Mar (Box 51, Folder 13)
    - Fan Clubs, 1960s and 1985 (Box 51, Folder 14)
      Photographs and newsletters.
    - Headshots of Malone (25 items), ca. 1950s-1970s (Box 51, Folder 15)
    - Azalea Festival - scrapbook pages of clippings, no date (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Long Hot Summer - scrapbook pages of clippings, 1965-1967 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Time Out for Ginger - scrapbook pages of clippings, 1953-1954 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Trial of the Catonsville Nine (The) -posters, 1971 (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbook pages of clippings, no date (Box 54, Folder 7)
      With Crystal and Fox, A Touch of the Poet, and Major Barbara.
    - First professional photograph of Nancy Malone (at age 6 or 7), no date (Box 58, Folder 10)
- Activism
  - unspecified
    - Women's Movement Affirmative Action articles and clippings, 1976 Mar-Apr, 1977 Feb, 1979 Jan (Box 49, Folder 11)
    - Women and Minorities on Television - reports, 1974, 1979, 1993 (Box 49, Folder 12)
      With: Los Angeles Television Coverage of Women's Concerns (May 1974); Women and Minorities in Television Drama 1969-1978 (Oct 1979); Women and Minorities on Television: A Study In Casting and Fate (June 15, 1993).
    - 20th Century Fox Women's Council, 1976 May-Jun (Box 51, Folder 1)
      Letters, photographs, and information related to self development and career planning workshop.
    - Women's Conference Committee, 1975, 2003 (Box 51, Folder 2)
      Meeting flier, tear out from Screen Actor newsletter, and communication re. unknown event.
    - Women's March on Washington (folder 1 of 2), 2004 April (Box 51, Folder 3)
      Correspondence, photographs, and clippings. T-shirt and ephemera moved to Box 52 for preservation purposes.
    - Women's March on Washington (folder 2 of 2), 2004 April (Box 52)
      From Box 51. T-shirt, buttons, and sash.
    - Women and Commercial TV Current Research, 1978-1979, 1986-1987 (Box 58, Folder 8)
      Letters and Representative Patricia Schroeder's speech transcript.
    - Directors Guild of America Women and working conditions, 1990-1991; 1997-1998 (Box 58, Folder 11)
      With reports from the National Committee on Working Women and DGA statistics on employment.
- Art and Poetry
  - unspecified
    - M and M Portfolio (folder 2 of 2), 1971 (Box 40, Folder 6)
      Oversize loose items found in or with portfolio.
    - M and M Portfolio (folder 1 of 2), 1971 (Box 51, Folder 10)
      Items removed from portfolio and re-housed in Mylar for preservation purposes. Pages numbered to keep original order.
    - Poetry Theaters, 1958, 1960-1961 (Box 51, Folder 11)
      Photographs and ephemera.
    - Artwork exhibitions, 1954, 1967, 2009 (Box 51, Folder 12)
      Clippings, snapshot of Eddie Bracken and photocopied photographs of artwork. Booklet documenting preparation of kiosks for Dolores Hope's 100th birthday.
- Directing
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - unspecified
    - Death of a Miner (The), 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Script and notes.
    - Agnes of God, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Script, music cues, program and contact sheet.
    - Prelude to a Kiss, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Published script, program, contact sheet and notecards.
    - Country Girl (The), 2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Scripts, program, contact sheet and notes.
    - Old Times, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Program, photos, and incomplete script.
    - Howie the Rookie - correspondence (email), 2005 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Howie the Rookie - clippings, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Howie the Rookie, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Set sound budget, notes, emails.
    - Howie the Rookie - rehearsal and performance reports, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Howie the Rookie - press kit, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Howie the Rookie, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Theater program, reviews, notices, information pertaining to stage space and printout of photograph with Malone and Ang Lee.
    - Howie the Rookie Press, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Photocopy of published script, notes, ephemera, clippings, well wishes and snapshots.
    - Railroad Women - script, no date (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Railroad Women, 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Photographs, clippings and notes. Program for Women's Writes festival.
    - All The Way Home, no date (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Photocopy of published script.
    - All The Way Home, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      Photographs, clippings, notes, theatre program, and set design.
    - Big Maggie, 1969 copyright (Box 8, Folder 7)
      Typescript of playscript. Original and photocopied Samuel French script.
    - Big Maggie, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Budget information, well wishes and actor headshots.
    - Dynasty - Surrogate (The), 1987 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Revised final draft script and production material.
    - Dynasty - Spoiler (The), 1987 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Third revised final draft script and production material.
    - Dynast - Valez, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      Final draft script and production material.
    - Dynasty - She's Back, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Dynasty - Adam's Son, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Final, second revised final and third revised final scripts and production material.
    - Dynasty - Grime and Punishment, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Dynasty - Alexis in Blunderland, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Final draft script, production material, and set plans.
    - Dynasty - Will (The), 1984 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Clippings, production material, contract, set drawings, and screen shot of Malone credit.
    - Dynasty - Will (The), 1984 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Final draft and photocopy of second draft scripts and additional script pages.
    - Dynasty - Reconciliation, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      First draft and heavily annotated revised final draft script and production material. Story outline for The Rescue.
    - Dynasty - Reconciliation, 1985 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Set plans.
    - Dynasty - Test (The), 1986 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Dynasty - Suspicions, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Revised final script, production material, and stage plans.
    - Dynasty - Rescue (The), 1986 (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Revised final draft script, production material, and stage plans.
    - Dynasty - Romance, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Revised final script, production material and set plans.
    - Dynasty - Ball (The), 1986 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Dynasty - Portrait (The), 1986 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Revised final script, production material, and set plans.
    - Bob Hope Christmas Show: Hopes for the Holidays, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Script and script material, production material and set plans.
    - Dynasty II: The Colbys of California - Moment of Truth, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Final draft script, production material and set plans.
    - Diagnosis Murder - Santa Claude, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      First draft script, production material and set plans.
    - Diagnosis Murder - Two Birds With One Sloan, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      Two first draft scripts and production material.
    - Diagnosis Murder - Sleight of Hand, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Production draft script, teaser, production material, set plans and two Polaroids with Malone and actresses.
    - Diagnosis Murder - You Bet Your Life, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Production draft script, production material and set plans.
    - Hotel - Aftershocks, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      Second draft script, production material and set plans.
    - Hotel - Fallen Angels, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Final draft script, added scene pages and production material.
    - Hotel - Contest of Wills, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Hotel - Revelations, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Second draft script and production material.
    - Hotel - Past Tense, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      Fourth draft script, production material and set plans.)
    - Hotel - Opening Moves, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Two copies of first draft script, production material and set plans. Black and white snapshot of Malone greeting James Brolin.
    - Hotel - Horizons, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      Second draft script, photograph of Anne Baxter, production materials and set plans.